<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC
        "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN"
        "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">
<html xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <head>
        <title>Lab #0: Python and scikit-learn</title>
    </head>
    <body>
        <!--<h1>Lab #0: Python and scikit-learn</h1>-->
        <h2>Objectives</h2>
        <p>The objectives of this lab are to:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>Be sure that you can log on the computer system</li>
            <li>Have the right programming environment</li>
            <li>Have a hands-on introduction to Python</li>
            <li>Know of a few Unix tools to derive word statistics</li>
            <li>Know of the main functions of scikit-learn</li>
        </ul>
        <p>The student's presence in the computer room through Zoom is not compulsory for this initial session.
            Its goal
            is to be sure that all the students have the elementary Python programming skills they need for the course.
            This means that if you know Python and scikit-learn (well enough), you can skip the lab.
            However, each student will have to run a short program at home on spelling correction and comment it.
            This last exercise is compulsory as well as handing in the report. See the last section of the page.
        </p>
        <h2>Organization and location</h2>
        <p>The initial lab session will take place on</p>
        <ol>
            <li>Group 1, September 1, 2020, 10:15 to 12:00, in the Alpha room,
                <br/>
                Discord link: https://discord.gg/83wWpF7
                <br/>
            </li>
            <li>group 2, September 1, 2020, 13:15 to 15:00, in the Alpha room,
                <br/>
                Discord link: https://discord.gg/83wWpF7
                <br/>
            </li>
            <li>group 3, September 2, 2020, 13:15 to 15:00, in the Val room,
                <br/>
                Discord link: https://discord.gg/83wWpF7
                <br/>
            </li>
            <li>group 4, September 2, 2020, 13:15 to 15:00, in the Falk rooms,
                <br/>
                Discord link: https://discord.gg/83wWpF7
                <br/>
            </li>
            <li>group 5, September 2, 2020, 15:15 to 17:00, in the Val room,
                <br/>
                Discord link: https://discord.gg/83wWpF7
                <br/>
            </li>
            <li>group 6, September 2, 2020, 15:15 to 17:00, in the Falk room.
                <br/>
                Discord link: https://discord.gg/83wWpF7
                <br/>
            </li>
        </ol>
        <p>There can be last minute changes. Please always check the official times here:
            <a
                    href="https://cloud.timeedit.net/lu/web/lth1/ri1X50gQ5560YfQQ15Z5772Y0Zy7007335Y67Q565.html">
                https://cloud.timeedit.net/lu/web/lth1/ri1Q5006.html
            </a>
        </p>
        <p>In this lab, we will review the Python syntax and some tools. Attendance is not compulsory,
            but you have to run the spell checker by Peter Norvig at home to make sure
            you understand Python.
        </p>
        <h2>Outline</h2>
        <ol>
            <li>We will use Python 3 and the Anaconda distribution in the labs:
                <a href="https://www.anaconda.com/distribution">https://www.anaconda.com/distribution</a>.
                Anaconda has most packages we need for the course.
            </li>
            <li>Anaconda is available on the LTH lab machines. You add it to your path by running:
                <br/>
                <tt>$ initcs</tt>
                <br/>
                If you use a personal machine, you will have to download and install it.
            </li>
            <li>
                <tt>regex</tt>
                is one of the few modules that is not in Anaconda:
                <a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/regex/">https://pypi.python.org/pypi/regex/</a>.
                <br/>
                <tt>regex</tt>
                can handle regular expressions and Unicode. It should already be installed on the computer network.
                On your personal machine, install it with <tt>pip</tt>:
                <br/>
                <tt>python -m pip install --upgrade regex</tt>
            </li>
            <li>You will carry out the labs with Jupyter notebooks. We will write code
                snippets (cells) that you will run interactively.
                You start jupyter with:
                <br/>
                <tt>$ jupyter lab</tt>
                <br/>
                or
                <br/>
                <tt>$ jupyter notebook</tt>
            </li>
            <li>Instead of an IDE, you may prefer a programming environment (IDE). I recommend PyCharm:
                <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/pycharm/">https://www.jetbrains.com/pycharm/</a>.
                The community edition is free.
                <br/>
                PyCharm should be available on the lab computers. If not, you will add the Python plugin to IntelliJ
                instead.
                Run:
                <br/>
                <tt>$ intellij-idea-community</tt>
                <br/>
                then Configure and add Python
            </li>
            <li>
                On the LTH machines, the <tt>regex</tt> module is not available from PyCharm by default.
                You need first to configure your environment. To do so, in the File menu, select
                Settings..., then Project and Project Interpreter. In the Project Interpreter box,
                on the top of the right pane, add the new interpreter by pressing the cog icon, and Add...
                Then select Anaconda Python:
                <tt>/usr/local/anaconda3/bin/python</tt>
            </li>
        </ol>
        <h2>Course of the lab</h2>
        <p>In the lab session, your instructors will walk you through Python, Unix, and scikit-learn. You will:</p>
        <ol>
            <li>run all the code in the chapter: A Tour of Python available here
                <a href="https://github.com/pnugues/edan20/tree/master/notebooks">
                    https://github.com/pnugues/edan20/tree/master/notebooks
                </a>
            </li>
            <li>count the words of a text with Unix tools</li>
            <li>run the quick introduction to scikit-learn:
                <a href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/tutorial/basic/tutorial.html">
                    https://scikit-learn.org/stable/tutorial/basic/tutorial.html
                </a>
                and understand <tt>fit()</tt> and <tt>predict()</tt>.
            </li>
        </ol>
        <h2>Compulsory part</h2>
        <ol>
            <li>Run the spell checker here: <a href="http://norvig.com/spell-correct.html">
                http://norvig.com/spell-correct.html</a>. Use Python 3 and make sure you understand all the code and
                Python syntax;
            </li>
            <li>Hand in an individual comment of this program on one to two pages (not more). To
                write this report, please use the overleaf site (<a href="https://www.overleaf.com/">
                    www.overleaf.com</a>)
                and Latex. Once you are done, please send the overleaf link to it (not the PDF) to the EDAN20 course
                address.
                Please check your document with a spell checker before you send it.
            </li>
        </ol>
    </body>
</html>
