<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC
        "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN"
        "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">
<html xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <head>
        <title>Assignment #3: Extracting noun groups using machine learning techniques</title>
    </head>
    <body>
        <!--<h1>Assignment #3: Extracting noun groups using machine learning techniques</h1>-->
        <h2>Objectives</h2>
        <p>The objectives of this assignment are to:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>Write a program to detect partial syntactic structures</li>
            <li>Understand the principles of supervised machine learning techniques applied to language processing</li>
            <li>Use a popular machine learning toolkit: scikit-learn</li>
            <li>Write a short report of 1 to 2 pages on the assignment</li>
        </ul>
        <h2>Organization and location</h2>
        <p>The third lab session will take place on</p>
        <ul>
            <li>Group 1: Tuesday, September 24 from 8:15 to 10:00 in the Alpha room</li>
            <li>Group 2: Tuesday, September 24 from 10:15 to 12:00 in the Alpha room</li>
            <li>Group 3: Tuesday, September 24 from 13:15 to 15:00 in the Alpha room</li>
            <li>Group 4: Tuesday, September 24 from 13:15 to 15:00 in the Beta room</li>
            <li>Group 5: Wednesday, September 25 from 13:15 to 15:00 in the Falk room</li>
            <li>Group 6: Wednesday, September 25 from 15:15 to 17:00 in the Falk room</li>
        </ul>
        <p>There can be last minute changes. Please always check the official times here:
            <a href="https://cloud.timeedit.net/lu/web/lth1/ri14566340000YQQ45Z5577007y5Y3713gQ5g5X6Y55ZQ076.html">
                https://cloud.timeedit.net/lu/web/lth1/ri1Q5006.html
            </a>
        </p>
        <p>You can work alone or collaborate with another student.</p>
        <p>Each group will have to:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>Write and train a machine-learning program to detect noun groups.</li>
            <li>Evaluate the results and comment them briefly.</li>
        </ul>
        <h2>Programming</h2>
        <h3>Choosing a training and a test sets</h3>
        <ol>
            <li>As annotated data and annotation scheme, you will use the data available from <a
                    href="https://www.clips.uantwerpen.be/conll2000/chunking/">CoNLL 2000</a>.
            </li>
            <li>Download both the training and test sets (the same as in
                the previous assignment) and decompress them.
                <br/>
                (Local copies available here: [<a
                        href="http://fileadmin.cs.lth.se/cs/Education/EDAN20/corpus/conll2000/train.txt">train.txt</a>]
                [<a href="http://fileadmin.cs.lth.se/cs/Education/EDAN20/corpus/conll2000/test.txt">test.txt</a>].)
            </li>
            <li>Be sure that you have the
                <a href="http://scikit-learn.org">scikit-learn</a>
                package:
                Start it by typing <tt>import sklearn</tt> in Python.
            </li>
        </ol>
        <h3>Baseline</h3>
        <p>Most statistical algorithms for language processing start with a so-called baseline. The baseline figure
            corresponds to the application of a minimal technique that is used to assess the difficulty of a task and
            for comparison with further programs.
        </p>
        <ol>
            <li>Read the baseline proposed by the organizers of the
                <a href="https://www.clips.uantwerpen.be/conll2000/chunking/">CoNLL 2000 shared task</a>
                (In the <i>Results</i> Sect.). What do you think of it?
            </li>
            <li>Implement this baseline program. You may either create a completely new program or start from an
                existing program that you will modify [<a
                        href="https://github.com/pnugues/ilppp/tree/master/programs/labs/chunking/chunker_python/">
                    Program folder
                </a>].
                <ul>
                    <li>Complete the <tt>train</tt> function so that it computes the chunk
                        distribution for each part of speech. You will use the train file to derive your distribution
                        and
                        you will store the results in a dictionary. Below, you have an excerpt of the expected results:
                        <pre>
                            {'JJR':
                            {'I-ADVP': 17, 'I-ADJP': 45, 'I-NP': 204, 'B-ADVP': 63,
                            'B-PP': 2, 'B-ADJP': 111, 'B-NP': 382, 'B-VP': 2,
                            'I-VP': 11, 'O': 16},
                            'CC':
                            {'B-ADVP': 3, 'O': 3676, 'I-VP': 104, 'B-CONJP': 6,
                            'I-ADVP': 30, 'I-UCP': 2, 'I-PP': 24, 'I-ADJP': 26,
                            'I-NP': 1409, 'B-ADJP': 2, 'B-NP': 18, 'B-PP': 70,
                            'I-PRT': 1, 'B-VP': 1},
                            'NN':
                            {'B-LST': 2, 'I-INTJ': 2, 'B-ADVP': 38, 'O': 37,
                            'I-ADVP': 11, 'B-INTJ': 1, 'I-UCP': 2, 'B-UCP': 2,
                            'I-VP': 77, 'B-PRT': 2, 'I-ADJP': 41, 'I-NP': 24456,
                            'B-ADJP': 44, 'B-NP': 5160, 'B-PP': 15, 'B-VP': 257},
                            ...
                        </pre>
                    </li>
                    <li>For each part of speech, select the most frequent chunk. In the example above, you will
                        have (NN, I-NP)
                    </li>
                    <li>Using the resulting associations, apply your chunker to the test file.</li>
                    <li>You will store your results in an output file that has four columns. The
                        three first columns will be the input columns from the test file: word, part of speech,
                        and gold-standard chunk. You
                        will append the predicted chunk as the 4th column. Your output file should look like
                        the excerpt below:
                        <pre>
                            Rockwell NNP B-NP I-NP
                            International NNP I-NP I-NP
                            Corp. NNP I-NP I-NP
                            's POS B-NP B-NP
                            Tulsa NNP I-NP I-NP
                            unit NN I-NP I-NP
                            said VBD B-VP B-VP
                            it PRP B-NP B-NP
                        </pre>
                        The CoNLL 2000 evaluation script
                        will use these
                        two last columns, chunk and predicted chunk, to compute the performance.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </li>

            <li>Measure the performance of the system. Use the
                <!--               <a href="https://github.com/pnugues/ilppp/tree/master/programs/corpus/conll2000">
                                   <tt>eval.sh</tt>
                               </a>
                               script or the-->
                <a href="https://www.clips.uantwerpen.be/conll2000/chunking/">
                    <tt>conlleval.txt</tt>
                </a>
                evaluation program used by the CoNLL 2000 shared task.
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <tt>conlleval.txt</tt>
                        is the official
                        CoNLL Perl script. It expects the two last columns of the test set to be the manually
                        assigned chunk (gold standard) and the predicted chunk.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Start it like this:
                        <pre>
                            $ conlleval.txt &lt;out
                        </pre>
                        where the <tt>out</tt> file contains both the gold and predicted chunk tags. <tt>conlleval.txt
                    </tt> is
                        a Perl script.
                    </li>
                    <li>Perl is installed on most Unix distributions. If it is not installed on your machine, you need
                        to install it.
                        Make also sure that
                        you have the execution rights. Otherwise change them with:
                        <pre>
                            $ chmod +x conlleval.txt
                        </pre>
                    </li>
                    <li>The <tt>conlleval.txt</tt> script expects the new lines to be <tt>\n</tt> as in Unix.
                        If you run your Python program on Windows, your new lines will be <tt>\r\n</tt>.
                        To have the correct new lines, add this parameter to <tt>open()</tt>:
                        <tt>newline='\n’</tt>
                        like this:
                        <pre>
                            f_out = open('out', ‘w’, newline='\n’)
                        </pre>
                    </li>
                    <li>The complete description of the CoNLL 2000 evaluation script is available here:
                        <a href="https://www.clips.uantwerpen.be/conll2000/chunking/output.html">
                            https://www.clips.uantwerpen.be/conll2000/chunking/output.html</a>.
                    </li>
                    <!--<li><tt>eval.sh</tt> is a convenience script 
                        that takes two test files as input, the gold and the prediction, and appends the last column of the predication
                        to the gold file. The output can then be passed to <tt>conlleval.txt</tt>. You run it this way:
                        <pre>
$ eval.sh test.txt out
                        </pre>
                        where <tt>test.txt</tt> is the gold test file, i.e. the test file with the answers, and the <tt>out</tt> file is your system's output.
                    </li>-->
                </ul>
            </li>
        </ol>
        <h3>Using Machine Learning</h3>

        <p>In this exercise, you will apply and extend the
            <tt>ml_chunker.py</tt>
            program. You will start from the original
            program you downloaded and modify it so that you understand
            how to improve the performance of your chunker. You will not add new features to the feature vector.
        </p>
        <p>The program that won the CoNLL 2000 shared task (Kudoh and Matsumoto, 2000) used a window of five words
            around the chunk tag to identify,
            <i>c
                <sub>i</sub>
            </i>
            . They built a feature vector consisting of:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li>The values of the five words in this window:
                <i>w
                    <sub>i-2</sub>
                </i>
                ,
                <i>w
                    <sub>i-1</sub>
                </i>
                ,
                <i>w
                    <sub>i</sub>
                </i>
                ,
                <i>w
                    <sub>i+1</sub>
                </i>
                ,
                <i>w
                    <sub>i+2</sub>
                </i>
            </li>
            <li>The values of the five parts of speech in this window:
                <i>t
                    <sub>i-2</sub>
                </i>
                ,
                <i>t
                    <sub>i-1</sub>
                </i>
                ,
                <i>t
                    <sub>i</sub>
                </i>
                ,
                <i>t
                    <sub>i+1</sub>
                </i>
                ,
                <i>t
                    <sub>i+2</sub>
                </i>
            </li>
            <li>The values of the two previous chunk tags in the first part of the window:
                <i>c
                    <sub>i-2</sub>
                </i>
                ,
                <i>c
                    <sub>i-1</sub>
                </i>
            </li>
        </ul>
        <p>The two last parameters are said to be dynamic because the program computes them at run-time. Kudoh and
            Matsumoto trained a classifier based on support vector machines. Read
            <a href="http://www.clips.uantwerpen.be/conll2000/pdf/14244kud.pdf">Kudoh and Matsumoto's paper</a>
            and the
            <a href="http://www.chasen.org/~taku/software/yamcha/">Yamcha</a>
            software site.
        </p>
        <ol>
            <li>What is the feature vector that corresponds to the <tt>ml_chunker.py</tt> program? Is it the same Kudoh
                and Matsumoto used in their experiment?
            </li>
            <li>What is the performance of the chunker?</li>
            <li>Remove the lexical features (the words) from the feature vector and measure the performance. You should
                observe a decrease.
            </li>
            <li>What is the classifier used in the program? Try two other classifiers and measure their performance:
                decision trees, perceptron, support vector machines, etc..
                Be aware that support vector machines take a long time to train: up to one hour.
            </li>
        </ol>
        <h3>Improving the Chunker</h3>
        <p>Implement one of these two options, the first one being easier.</p>
        <ol>
            <li>Complement the feature vector used in the previous section with the two dynamic features,
                <i>c
                    <sub>i-2</sub>
                </i>
                ,
                <i>c
                    <sub>i-1</sub>
                </i>
                , and train a new model. You will need to modify the
                <tt>extract_features_sent</tt>
                and <tt>predict</tt> functions.
                <br/>
                In his experiments, your teacher obtained a F1 score of
                92.33 with a dual L2-regularized logistic regression;
            </li>
            <li>
                If you know what beam search is, apply it using the probability output of logistic
                regression or
                the score if you use support vector machines.
                <br/>
                With the same classifier and a beam diameter of 5, your teacher obtained 92.56.
            </li>
        </ol>
        <p>
            <b>A frequent mistake in the labs</b>
            is to use the gold-standard chunks from the test set. Be aware that
            when you predict the test set, you do not know the dynamic features in advance and you must
            not use the ones from the test file.
            You will use the two previous chunk tags that you have predicted.
        </p>
        <p>You need to reach a global F1 score of 92 to pass this laboratory.
        </p>

    </body>
</html>
