<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC
        "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN"
        "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">
<html xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <head>
        <title>EDAN20 – Language Technology</title>
    </head>
    <body>
        <!--<h1>EDAN20 – Language Technology</h1>-->
        <p><b>This page is provisional is is being constantly updated</b></p>
        <p>This year, we will have no physical lecture classes or labs. We will be using Zoom
            for the whole course.</p>
        <p>The schedule for August/September/October 2020 is available here: <a
                href="https://cloud.timeedit.net/lu/web/lth1/ri1X50gQ5560YfQQ15Z5772Y0Zy7007335Y67Q565.html">
            https://cloud.timeedit.net/lu/web/lth1/ri1Q5006.html</a>. Use the
            <i>course schedule</i>
            or <i>lässchema</i> links and enter EDAN20 to view the course schedule.
        </p>
        <p>
            Registration
            <br/>
            You need to attend the first lecture to be sure to keep your seat (or email the course leader before
            the course starts). You should formally register in the LADOK system, preferably before the course starts.
            You have the instructions here in <a
                href="http://www.student.lth.se/studieinformation/registreringar/">Swedish
        </a> and
            in <a
                href="https://www.lth.se/english/education/master/information-for-current-students/course-registration/">
            English</a>. If you fail to register, the department might register you
            anyway, if you attended the first lecture.
        </p>
        <!--		<p>Due to a meeting in Gothenburg on September 13, 2011, the class is cancelled for this date (13/09/2011). It will be replaced by a lecture on September 23, room E:B.
                </p>-->
        <p>The first lecture will be held on August 31, 2019, 15-17. We will use Zoom. Please install it before the
            the lecture starts.
        </p>
        <p>The course takes place in the HT1 “study period.”
        </p>
        <p>
            You can register to a laboratory group here:
            <a
                    href="https://sam.cs.lth.se/LabsSelectSession?occasionId=656">
                https://sam.cs.lth.se/LabsSelectSession?occasionId=656
            </a>
        </p>
        <h2>Objectives</h2>
        <p>The course introduces theories and techniques of natural language processing and language technology. It
            attempts to cover the whole field from speech recognition and synthesis to semantics and dialogue.
        </p>
        <p>It focuses on industrial or laboratory applications, such as document retrieval on the Internet, information
            extraction, conversational agents, and verbal interaction in virtual worlds. Fundamental algorithms will be
            described using Python.
        </p>
        <h2>Course contents</h2>
        <ul>
            <li>An overview of language processing: presentation of language processing, applications, disciplines of
                linguistic, examples
            </li>
            <li>Corpus and word processing: regular expressions, automata, an introduction to Python, concordances,
                tokenization, counting words, collocations
            </li>
            <li>Morphology and part-of-speech tagging: morphology, transducers, part-of-speech tagging,</li>
            <li>Prolog to write phrase-structure grammars: constituents, trees, using Prolog to do natural language
                analysis, DCG rules, variables, getting the syntactic structure, compositional analysis to get the
                semantic structure.
            </li>
            <li>Syntactic formalisms: constituency and dependency, chart parsing, statistical parsing, functions,
                dependency parsing.
            </li>
            <li>Semantics: formal semantics, lambda-calculus, compositionality: nouns, verbs, determiners, words and
                meaning, lexical semantics, case grammars, semantic grammars
            </li>
            <li>Discourse and dialogue: discourse and rhetoric, anaphora, structure, RST, dialogue: automata, pairs,
                speech acts, multimodality.
            </li>
            <li>Overview of speech synthesis and speech recognition</li>
        </ul>
        <h2>Textbook</h2>
        <p>As textbook, I will use:<i>Language processing with Perl and Prolog</i>, 2nd edition, 2014, Springer. It is
            available from Springer link: [<a href="http://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-3-642-41464-0">html</a>] [<a
                    href="http://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007/978-3-642-41464-0.pdf">pdf</a>], or in a paper
            version
            [<a href="http://www.springer.com/computer/ai/book/978-3-642-41463-3">html</a>].
        </p>
        <p>I started to write a 3rd edition with Python instead of Perl. Unfortunately, on August 15, 2016,
            I had a work accident at LTH: Workers demolished the window of my office
            while I was working and without warning me.
            Since then, I have a very debilitating tinnitus (ringing hears).
            This new edition will be considerably delayed (if I can ever publish it).
            I will nonetheless hand out a draft of the chapters I have written.
        </p>
        <p>Students can also use the first edition from 2006,<i>An Introduction to Language Processing with Perl and
            Prolog</i>. The electronic version is available for free: [<a
                href="http://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007/3-540-34336-9.pdf">pdf</a>]. You need to be logged
            from Lund University accounts to have a free copy. The paper version of the first edition costs 25 euros:
            [<a href="http://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/3-540-34336-9">html</a>].
        </p>
        <p>
            <strong>Ges:</strong>
            Läsperiod HT1
        </p>
        <p>
            <strong>Kontaktperson:</strong>
            Pierre Nugues
        </p>
        <p>
            <strong>Förkunskapskrav:</strong>
            Se <a href="https://kurser.lth.se/kursplaner/19_20/EDAN20.html">kursplanen</a>.
        </p>
        <p>
            <strong>OBS! Kursen ges på engelska</strong>
        </p>
        <p>
            <strong>Kurswebb:</strong>
            <a href="http://cs.lth.se/edan20">http://cs.lth.se/edan20</a>
        </p>
    </body>
</html>